各部门，安全检查中，报告进度
All sections, security check in progress. Report.
- 前部相位炮，正常 - 已驶入标准轨道，护士
- Forward phaser, affirmative. - We're entering standard orbit, nurse.
不用太久
Won't be much longer.
前向传感器接至舰桥…
Forward scanner to bridge.
我知道你为何放弃生物研究
I understand you gave up a career in bioresearch
报名来到星舰的原因
to sign aboard a starship.
我知道他还活着，舰长
I know he's alive down there, captain.
后向传感器接至舰桥，情况正常
Aft scanner to bridge. Status report, green.
引擎控制…
Engineering controls...
上次和他通话已是五年前的事了
It's been five years since his last message.
罗杰很坚强，他总能设法活下去
Roger's a very determined man. He'd find a way to live.
开始与地面通讯，长官
Beginning signals to surface, sir.
用所有频率传递信号，上尉
Put it on all frequencies, lieutenant.
关于这颗星球的信息
Ship's record banks show little we don't already know
星舰的资料库已有详细记录，舰长
about this planet, captain.
可星球地面温度只有零下100摄氏度
But the surface temperature of that planet is 100 degrees below zero.
这里曾经适宜居住，但这片星系的太阳
It may have been inhabited once, but the sun in this system
在过去50万年中不断衰退
has been fading steadily for a half-million years.
再说说科比博士，被大家称为考古医学的奠基人
Now, Dr. Korby, often called the Pasteur of archaeological medicine,
他翻译了从猎户座废墟挖掘出的医学记录
his translation of medical records from the Orion ruins
我们的免疫技术因此获得革命性突破
revolutionised our immunization techniques.
星舰学院必修的科目，史波克
Required reading at the Academy, Mr. Spock.
我一直想见见他
I've always wanted to meet him.
你觉得他还活着吗？
Do you think there's any chance of him still being alive?
所有频率都试过了，长官，没有回复
I've tried all frequencies, sir. No return signal.
接着试
Keep trying.
曲速机能0.07，正在增加
Warp capacity, 0.07 and building.
通讯官，脉冲引擎甲板需要更多通信线路
Communicator, we need more lines to the impulse deck.
他最后那通信息提到发现地下洞穴的事
His last signal told about finding underground caverns.
此后有两支探险队都找过他，但都一无所获
And since then, two expeditions have failed to find him.
所有频率又试了一遍，舰长，还是没…
I've run all frequencies a second time, captain. There's no--
进取号，请回话，进取号
Enterprise. Come in, Enterprise.
我是罗杰·科比，重复，我是罗杰·科比博士
This is Roger Korby. Repeating, this is Dr. Roger Korby.
收到了吗，进取号？我是罗杰·科比博士
Do you read me, Enterprise? This is Dr. Roger Korby.
待命
Standing by.
宇宙，最后的边疆
Space, the final frontier.
这是星舰进取号的航程
These are the voyages Of the starship Enterprise.
它的五年任务，是去探索未知的新世界
Its five-year mission: To explore strange new worlds,
找寻新的生命与新的文明
to seek out new life and new civilizations,
勇敢地航向前人未至之境
to boldly go where no man has gone before.
【星际迷航：原初】
荣誉出品
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业途径
=TLF字幕组=
翻译：kmdangdangli，土豆爱，jc
校对：kmdangdangli，Micezhang，xjCGI
第一季第七集：科比博士的新发现
舰长日志，星历2712.4
Captain's log, stardate 2712.4:
埃克索Ⅲ号行星发出信号，我们找到了罗杰·科比博士
A signal from planet Exo III. Dr. Roger Korby has been located.
他和探险队在地下发现了一片废墟
He and part of his expedition remaining alive
并在那儿活了下来
due to the discovery of underground ruins
那里曾是星球原住民的居住地
left by the former inhabitants of this world.
进取号呼叫科比
Enterprise to Korby.
我们已定位你所在的坐标
We have your landing coordinates pinpointed.
准备派遣一组外遣队下去
We're preparing to beam down a party.
还要特别告诉你，一同前来的还有…
It may interest you to know that we have aboard this vessel--
我有个不情之请，寇克舰长
I have a rather unusual request, Captain Kirk.
能只传送一个人下来吗？就你一人
Can you beam down alone, just yourself?
我们发现了一种生物
we've made discoveries of such a nature,
需要你做一个非同一般的决定
they may require an extraordinary decision from you.
这种要求的确少见
That is an unusual request.
对方可是罗杰·科比博士
The man making it is Dr. Roger Korby.
你肯定这是他的声音？
You're certain you'd recognise his voice?
你订过婚吗，史波克先生？
Have you ever been engaged, Mr. Spock?
没错，这是罗杰
Oh, yes. It's Roger.
好吧，博士，但还有一个人
Agreed, doctor. However, there will be two of us.
罗杰，你好吗？
Hello, Roger.
- 克莉丝汀？ - 正是，罗杰
- Christine? - Yes, Roger.
亲爱的，怎么…？你在哪？
Darling, how--? where are you?
好啊，没问题，让她来，舰长，我在这儿过得了无生趣
Yes, yes. By all means, captain. I had no idea, no hope.
- 亲爱的，你还好吗？ - 我很好，罗杰
- Darling, are you all right? - Yes, Roger.
现在一切都好了
Everything's all right now.
我们就快到了，博士，一会儿见
We're on our way, doctor. We'll be with you in a moment.
通话完毕
Enterprise out.
传送
Energize.
他说过在这儿等的
He said he'd be waiting.
科比博士？
Dr. Korby?
估计找错入口了
It's possible we might have hit the wrong entry point.
- 寇克呼叫进取号 - 史波克在此，舰长
- Kirk to Enterprise. - Spock here, captain.
传送…
Beam down...
- 两名安全人员下来 - 出什么事了，舰长？
- ...two security men. - Any problems, captain?
还没见到人，也许是我多虑了，通话完毕
Some delay in meeting us. Probably nothing at all. Kirk out.
估计通道很深
The corridors could be quite deep.
可能比预计会迟到一会儿
Getting here may have taken more time than he estimated.
- 别担心 - 谢谢
- Don't worry. - Thank you.
- 雷伯恩，原地待命 - 是，长官
- Rayburn, maintain post here. - Yes, sir.
马修斯，我们去找科比博士
Mathews, we'll look for Dr. Korby.
- 你和我们一起去 - 是，长官
- You accompany us. - Yes, sir.
你是科比博士吗？
Is that you, Dr. Korby?
布朗博士，罗杰的助手
Dr. Brown. It’s Roger's assistant.
布朗，罗杰在哪？
Brownie, where's Roger?
小心，得小心
Careful. Please be careful.
有下去的路吗？
Is there a path down there?
没希望了，舰长，下面是万丈深渊
There's no hope, captain. It's bottomless.
一定是不小心掉下去的
He must have slipped.
岩壁上有可攀岩的踏足点吗？
Any chance of a projection or a ledge?
没有，舰长
None, captain.
真不幸
Unfortunate.
太不幸了
Terribly unfortunate.
科比博士走不开，我尽快赶来了
Dr. Korby was detained. I came as soon as I could.
还是来晚了
But not soon enough.
布朗
Brownie.
- 你怎么了？ - 什么怎么了？
- What is it? - Explain.
你不认识我啦？
Don't you recognise me?
克莉丝汀
Christine.
你气色不错，我叫布朗，科比博士的助手
You look well. My name is Brown. Dr. Korby's assistant.
你便是寇克舰长吧？
I presume you are Captain Kirk?
他死了，我敢保证
He's dead. I assure you.
走吧，科比博士还等着呢
Come. Dr. Korby will be waiting.
他真是你认识的老朋友？
You do know him well. An old friend?
估计他在这儿呆了五年就…
Well, I suppose living here for five years...
寇克呼叫雷伯恩，有何情况？
Captain Kirk to Rayburn, report.
入口十分安静，舰长
All quiet here at the entry, captain.
你那边呢，长官？
Any problems there, sir?
马修斯死了
we lost Mathews.
像是意外所致
Apparently an accident.
让进取号准备一组安全队员全副武装，随时待命
Tell the Enterprise to have a full security party standing by.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
我们每小时通话一次
--that we'll both report in at hourly inteevals.
若你我失去联系
If you and I lose contact,
或其中任何人与进取号失去联系
or if he fails to hear from either of us,
就立即传送安全队下来
he's to beam the security party down immediately.
通话完毕
Kirk out.
科比博士发现，随着太阳衰退变暗
Dr. Korby has discovered that as their sun dimmed,
这儿的居民就迁至地下
the inhabitants of this planet moved underground,
从一个开阔的环境来到一个黑暗的世界
from an open environment to this dark world.
你还是他学生的时候，克莉丝汀
When you were a student of his, Christine,
一定常听科比博士说
you must have often heard Dr. Korby remark
行动和选择的自由赋予人类灵魂
how freedom of movement and choice produced the human spirit.
埃克索Ⅲ号行星的文化证实了他的理论
The culture of Exo III proved his theory.
当人们从光明来到黑暗之地后
When they moved from light to darkness,
自由便被一种机械式的文化取代
they replaced freedom with a mechanistic culture.
科比博士已经发现了这种文化的组成要素
Dr. Korby has been able to uncover elements of this culture
一旦他离开洞穴，重获自由
which will revolutionise the universe
便能改变整个宇宙
when freed from this cavernous environment.
我是安德烈娅
I'm Andrea.
你一定就是克莉丝汀
You must be Christine.
我一直觉得你的名字好美
I've always thought how beautiful your name is.
你一定就是进取号的寇克舰长
And you must be Captain Kirk of the starship Enterprise.
非常感谢你把罗杰的未婚妻带来
We appreciate you bringing Roger's fiancée to him.
我记得科比博士没提过什么安德烈娅
I don't remember Dr. Korby mentioning an Andrea.
但你长得和罗杰说的一模一样
But you are exactly as Roger described you.
难怪他这么想你
No wonder he missed you so.
- 科比博士在哪？ - 在这，舰长
- Where is Dr. Korby? - Here, captain.
我…
I...
我一直期待…
I've been looking forward to...
噢…我就知道能找到你
Oh, I knew I'd find you.
现在都没事了
Everything's all right now.
还请你原谅，舰长
Forgive me, captain.
我是…罗杰·科比
I'm-- I'm Roger Korby.
不用抱歉，先生
There's no need to apologise, sir,
更不用自我介绍
and certainly no need to introduce yourself.
舰长的一名部下死在了洞穴，博士
The captain lost a man in the caverns, doctor.
什么？
What?
- 怎么回事？ - 在洞穴外围附近
- How did it happen? - The pit near the outer junction.
从悬崖上失足落下的
The edge must have given way.
真抱歉，舰长
I'm terribly sorry, captain.
要是当时我在，我…我熟悉各个通道
Perhaps if I'd been there, I-- I know the passages so well.
这不是你的错
It wasn't your fault.
寇克呼叫雷伯恩，有何情况？
Kirk to Rayburn. Report.
我得回复确认安全
I'm required to make a security confirmation.
我和星舰通话时也请你提供一份人员名单
When I call my ship, if you'll list your personnel,
物品需求清单以及其他特殊需求
cargo requirements, any special needs--
- 你能… - 雷伯恩，能收到我的话吗？
- I'd much prefer-- - Rayburn, are you receiving me?
能再等等吗，舰长？好吗？有些话我要和你说
I'd prefer you waited, captain. Please. Till I’ve talked to you.
我已经和警卫失去联络，我必须和星舰联系
I've lost contact with my guard. I'm required to call my ship.
别再联系了，舰长
No communications, captain.
- 罗杰 - 对不起
- Roger. - I'm sorry.
如果他们再派人下来…
If they should send down more people...
- 罗杰，那个人… - 他不会再受到伤害，我保证
- Roger, that man is-- - He won't be harmed. I promise you.
这儿有些事你还不了解
Isn't it possible there could be things here unknown to you,
- 但却非常重要… - 先生，这儿死了一个人
- so terribly important that--? - Sir, one man is dead.
我和另一个也失去了联系
I've lost contact with the other.
安德烈娅
Andrea.
你要干嘛？
What are you doing?
我必须这样，舰长，你会明白的
This is necessary, captain. You will understand.
安德烈娅
Andrea.
把枪放下
Drop it.
寇克呼叫进取号，能听见吗？
Enterprise from Captain Kirk, come in. Do you read?
已开启频率，史波克先生
Frequency open, Mr. Spock.
我是史波克，舰长
Spock here, captain.
已见到科比博士
Contact established with Dr. Korby.
我们还在担心呢，舰长，你迟迟没有联系
We were becoming concerned, captain. Your check-in was overdue,
你的安全小组也没任何消息…
and since we'd not heard from your security team--
一切正常，史波克，让你担心了
No problem, Mr. Spock. Bear with me.
我们48小时内便返回星舰
We'll return to the ship within 48 hours.
科比博士的记录及收集的标本还得仔细装运
Dr. Korby's records and specimens will require careful packing.
舰长，你没事吧？你听上怎么有点累？
Captain, are you all right? You sound tired.
你动一下或叫一声，小心鲁格不客气
If you move or cry out, Ruk may injure you.
- 至少等我们谈完 - 请回复，舰长
- At least wait until you and I can talk. - Acknowledge, captain.
- 是否一切正常？ - 没事，史波克
- Is everything all right? - Fine, Mr. Spock.
科比博士有一些瞩目的发现
Dr. Korby has made some fascinating discoveries.
一切尽在掌握，待命保持联络，通话完毕
All under control. Stand by for regular contact. Kirk out.
这不只是作秀，舰长
This is not a vain display, captain.
我是科学家，你也知道我的名望
I'm a scientist. You obviously know of my reputation.
相信我
Trust me.
我的确知道你的名望
Yes, I know your reputation.
银河系无人不知，无人不晓
The whole galaxy knows who you are and what you stand for.
正因如此，这一切才说不通
That's why all this makes no sense.
很多事你了解之后再作判断
There is so much you must learn before you make a final judgement.
比如…
For example...
安德烈娅
...Andrea.
你一定就是进取号的寇克舰长
You must be Captain Kirk of the starship Enterprise.
克莉丝汀
Christine,
现在没事了
it's all right now.
- 看见了吗，舰长？ - 看见了，罗杰
- You see, captain? - Yes, Roger.
现在一切都好了
Everything is all right now.
够了
That's enough.
不许嘲弄克莉丝汀
You are not to mock Christine.
- 你永远不能伤害她 - 也不能违抗她的命令
- You will never harm her. - Or disobey an order from her.
不许违抗她的命令，满意了吗，寇克舰长？
You will not disobey her orders. Satisfied, Captain Kirk?
对她只有爱和信任
Both love and trust.
现在，给我24小时说服你
Now, give me 24 hours to convince you.
博士，没必要把我关起来才能说服我吧？
Doctor, do I need to be a prisoner to be convinced?
你回到星舰第一个任务是什么？
What would your first duty be upon return to your vessel?
是报告，你知道有多少探索发现
A report. Do you realise the number of discoveries lost
因为迷信，无知及外行的不解丧失了宝贵的价值？
because of superstition, of ignorance, of a layman's inability to comprehend?
那让我这个外行问个简单的问题，博士
Then a simple layman's question, doctor.
我其它的船员在哪？
Where is my other crewman?
是死？是活？
Alive? Dead?
为了保护我的实验，我为鲁格编了套程序
Ruk was programmed to protect my experiments.
他的机器大脑用逻辑推算我有危险
The logic of his machine mind saw a danger to me.
我其它的船员在哪？
Where is my other crewman?
他俩都被鲁格杀了
Ruk destroyed them both.
但这完全不是我的意思，我保证
But totally against my wishes, I assure you.
他是机器人？和布朗一样？
He's an android? Like Brown?
比布朗要复杂
More complex than Brown.
高级得多
Much superior.
我是留在这儿的老一代
I was left here by the Old Ones.
我们到这儿时鲁格就已在看管机器
Ruk was still tending the machinery when we arrived here.
多少世纪了？
How many centuries?
甚至鲁格都记不清了
Even Ruk doesn't know.
我们在他的帮助下，根据手头的资料造出了布朗
With his help, with the records I could find, we built Brown.
我已被你说服了，博士
You've convinced me, doctor.
现在我相信你是个危险人物
You've convinced me that you're dangerous.
鲁格，住手
Ruk, no.
我不明白
I do not understand.
你为何不开心？
Why are you unhappy?
你和罗杰不是又相聚了吗？
You are with Roger again.
寇克舰长在哪？
Where is Captain Kirk?
你为舰长担心？
You are concerned about the captain?
是的，我很担心
Yes, I’m concerned.
既然你爱罗杰，为什么又不信任他呢？
How can you love Roger without trusting him?
为什么我叫他罗杰，你会不开心呢？
Why does it bother you when I use the name Roger?
安德烈娅
Andrea,
你这样叫我的确会令她不开心
it's sufficient that it does disturb her.
今后你得叫我科比博士，安德烈娅
You will call me Dr. Korby from now on, Andrea.
是，科比博士
Yes, Dr. Korby.
我并非故意偷听你们的谈话，亲爱的
I didn't mean to eavesdrop, darling.
看见了吧，寇克舰长没事，我们不会伤害他
As you can see, Captain Kirk is fine. He won't be harmed.
最紧要的事情是只要他能保证
The things at stake here simply make it necessary
不向星舰汇报情况
he doesn't send a report to his ship.
我有东西给你们看，这需要时间
I need time to explain and demonstrate to him and to you.
那就从安德烈娅开始吧
Now, shall we start with Andrea?
行，从安德烈娅开始吧
Yes, let's start with Andrea.
我和布朗博士一样，是个机器人
I'm like Dr. Brown. An android.
你们看不出来吗？
Didn't you know?
不可思议吧？
Remarkable, isn't she?
看看…这逼真的肤色
Notice the-- The lifelike pigmentation.
皮肤色调的变化
The variation in skin tones.
肉体…肉体还有温度
The flesh-- The flesh has warmth.
甚至还有脉搏以及生理反应
There's even a pulse. Physical sensation.
岂不是方便了你？
How convenient.
克莉丝汀，你得明白机器人就像电脑
Christine, you must realise that an android is like a computer.
它的行为全由程序控制
It does only what I programme.
身为一名训练有素的科学家，你应该明白…
As a trained scientist yourself, you must realise--
既然能造个布朗博士，再造个艺妓
That given a mechanical Dr. Brown, then a mechanical geisha
还有何难？
would be no more difficult.
- 你认为我会爱上一台机器？ - 你爱上了吗？
- You think I could love a machine? - Did you?
安德烈娅不会爱，她只会服从命令
Andrea is incapable of that. She simply obeys orders.
她对我没有意思，我们之间没有感情
She has no meaning for me. There's no emotional bond.
安德烈娅
Andrea,
去吻寇克舰长
kiss Captain Kirk.
现在打他
Now strike him.
看到了吗？她没有感情
You see? There's no emotion in her,
她做事不带感情，只会服从命令
no emotional involvement. She simply responds to orders.
她只是台靠逻辑运算的电脑
She's a totally logical computer.
一件物品，而不是女人
A thing, yes, not a woman.
现在你明白了吗？
Now do you understand?
如果这些机器没有感情
If these mechanical things have no feelings,
只按照你的程序做事
and perform only as you programme them,
为什么他杀了我两名手下？
then why did Brown try to shoot me? Why did he kill two of my men?
我不明白的事还很多，博士
There are many things I don't understand, doctor.
我会回答你所有的问题…
I will answer all of your questions...
就现在
...now.
机器人就是这么造出来的
This is how you make an android.
安德烈娅
Andrea.
他不会有事，我保证
He's not being harmed. I promise.
罗杰，你这是怎么了？
Roger, what's happened to you?
记得你给我上课的时候
When I sat in your class, why, you wouldn't even dream
你甚至连一只虫子、动物都不敢伤害
of harming an insect or an animal.
那时生命对你何等神圣
No, life was sacred to you then.
克莉丝汀，如果我和布朗以及其他人
Christine, if I’d simply beamed up to their vessel
就这么登上星舰，我…
with Brown and the others, I--
我会成为好奇的对象
I'd have given them objects of curiosity,
别人会以为我的学说荒谬愚蠢
the beginnings of wild stories, foolish theories.
鲁格
Ruk.
看仔细了
Watch carefully.
选选看，克莉丝汀
Choose, Christine.
哪位是你的舰长
Which is your captain?
不知道
I don't know.
他们一模一样
They're exact.
我真不知道
I honestly don't know.
合成器官都已造好
Synthetic organs are in place.
只要和寇克的自主神经系统相连
We merely synchronize them with Kirk's autonomic nervous system,
便可复制他的身体律动
duplicating the rhythms of his body.
同时，还要复制思维模式
At the same time, we duplicate the mental patterns.
生理模式现已完成，接下来复制思维模式
Now, physical pattern complete, we now make a mental pattern.
准备最后的突触融合【突触连接神经元和肌细胞】
Ready for final synaptic fusion.
安德烈娅，准备接通大脑皮层电路
Andrea, stand by for cortex circuits.
将是个完美的机器人，甚至可以替代舰长
The android will be so perfect, he could even replace the captain.
拥有同样的记忆、态度和能力
The same memories, the same attitudes, the same abilities.
启动电路
Activate circuits.
别多管闲事了，史波克
Mind your own business, Mr. Spock.
你个杂种别再来烦我了，听见没？
I'm sick of your half-breed interference, do you hear?
别多管闲事了，史波克，你个混球别再…
Mind your own business, Mr. Spock. I'm sick of your half-breed--
完成了
Complete.
你没事吧？
Are you all right?
目前没事
As far as I know.
现在
And now,
见一下机器人
meet an android.
你好吗，查佩尔小姐？
How do you do, Miss Chapel?
我现在有取悦你的程序
I am now programmed to please you also.
食物合你胃口吗？
Is the food appealing?
是的，谢谢
Yes, thank you.
- 请坐，舰长 - 谢谢
- Please sit, captain. - Thank you.
我想我基本上就算是获释了
I'm more or less on parole, I understand.
科比博士让您吃午饭
Dr. Korby suggested that you have lunch.
他猜你们有话要说
He thought you might have a few things to talk about.
- 舰长… - 我知道，我知道
- Captain-- - I know, I know.
一边是长官，一边是未婚夫，的确很为难
I'd hate to be torn between commander and fiancé myself.
不，我…我不为难
No, I'm-- I'm not torn.
我只是困惑，我很担心
I'm puzzled. I’m worried.
- 他告诉你了吗？ - 对你说的，他都对我说了
- Has he confided in you? - Nothing he hasn't told you.
我知道这说不通
I know it doesn't make sense.
他这样做是不对，可他毕竟是罗杰·科比
What he's done may seem wrong, but he is Roger Korby,
不管他做了什么，不管他下一步要做什么
whatever he seems to be doing.
除非他脑袋有问题
Unless something's gone wrong with his mind.
不可能，我了解他
No, you're forgetting how well I know him.
他神志清楚，和你我一样
He's as sane as you or I.
护士…
Nurse...
如果我命令你，让你背叛他…？
...if I gave you a direct order to betray him...?
不会吧
Please.
不要让我做这种选择
Don't ask me to make that choice.
否则，我宁愿被你推下悬崖
No, I'd much rather you push me off the same precipice
就从马修斯掉下的地方
where Mathews died.
哦，不，我没胃口
Oh, no, I can't.
你接着吃
Please go ahead and eat.
机器人是不吃东西的，查佩尔小姐
Androids don't eat, Miss Chapel.
他甚至具有你的幽默感
He even has your sense of humour.
我们还是有一点不同，我会饿
Well, there's one difference between us, I'm hungry.
而这成了你的弱点，舰长，我没有
The difference is your weakness, captain, not mine.
有话慢慢说，先生们，舰长？
One at a time, gentlemen. Captain?
吃东西是件乐事，先生，可惜你永远都体会不到
Eating is a pleasure, sir. Unfortunately, one you will never know.
也许吧，但我永远都不会挨饿，先生
Perhaps. But I will never starve, sir.
- 他真是我的复制品？ - 从头到脚
- He's an exact duplicate? - In every detail.
记忆呢？和我讲讲萨姆
What about memory? Tell me about Sam.
乔治·塞缪尔·寇克，你弟弟，只有你叫他萨姆
George Samuel Kirk. Your brother. Only you call him Sam.
这次任务临行前，是他送的我
He saw me off on this mission.
对，连同他妻子及三个儿子
Yes, with his wife and three sons.
他说他将被调到地球殖民地2号的研究站
He said he was being transferred to Earth Colony 2 research station.
不对，舰长，他说他还在搞他的研究
No, captain. He said he was continuing his research,
并希望能被派到地球殖民地2号
and that he wanted to be transferred to Earth Colony 2.
你们不妨再比比运算能力
You might as well try to outthink a calculating machine.
很显然，我不如他
Obviously, I can't.
但是我们确实有一些有趣的差别
But we do have some interesting differences.
都是些无关紧要的差别
Totally unimportant ones.
你现在可以走了
You may leave now.
猜猜接下来会怎样？
You haven't guessed the rest?
连你也猜不出，克莉丝汀？
Not even you, Christine?
你看到的只是一台机器
What you saw was only a machine.
只是个半成品，知道吗？
Only half of what I could have accomplished. Do you understand?
让我继续的话，我就能完全转移你的意识
By continuing the process, I could have transferred you,
进入那个机器人的身体
your very consciousness, into that android.
包括灵魂，只要你想，你的全部
Your soul, if you wish. All of you.
拥有机器身躯的人类便可真正获得永生
In android form, a human being can have practical immortality.
知道我为人类做的贡献了吧？
Can you understand what I'm offering Mankind?
编程
Programming.
成吉思汗、凯撒、希特勒、费里斯、马尔图维斯
Different word, but the same old promises made by Genghis Khan,
都这样说过，用词不同而已
Julius Caesar, Hitler, Ferris, Maltuvis.
知道人一旦变成机器人之后
Can you understand that a human converted to an android
便可通过程序改善自身吗？
can be programmed for the better?
你能想象一个没有嫉妒、贪婪、憎恨的生活
Can you imagine how life could be improved
会多么美好吗？
if we could do away with jealousy, greed, hate?
何不把爱情、温情、情感也统统抹去？
It can also be improved by eliminating love, tenderness, sentiment.
有利必有弊，博士
The other side of the coin, doctor.
不会再有人死去
No one need ever die again.
也没有疾病、残疾
No disease, no deformities.
通过程序连恐惧也能被快乐代替
Why, even fear can be programmed away and replaced with joy.
我正为人类打造天堂，一片全新的乐土
I'm offering you a practical heaven, a new paradise.
只要你肯帮我
And all I need is your help.
你所有的期望，我能理解
All you wanted before was my understanding.
我需要找一颗殖民行星，拥有合适的原材料
I need transportation to a planet colony with the proper raw materials.
你随后的航程中，肯定能遇到合适的
Now, I’m sure there are several good possibilities among your next stops.
不用改变航线，别人会因此疑心
No diversion from your route. I want no suspicions aroused.
我会认真，有选择性地制造机器人
I'll begin producing androids carefully, selectively.
是啊，是啊，这件事得保密
Yes. Yes. No one need know.
不知道的人听了也会被吓到
No need to frighten uninformed minds.
在透露这个秘密之前
They must be strongly infiltrated into society
先让机器人融入人类社会
before the android existence is revealed.
我不想让疯狂的人类把美好正确的东西毁掉
I want no wave of hysteria to destroy what is good and right.
你能理解我了吗，舰长？
Are you with me, captain?
你已经创造了你自己的寇克
You've created your own Kirk.
为什么还需要我呢？
Why do you need me?
我只想给你留下深刻印象，而不是取代你
I created him to impress you, not to replace you.
的确印象深刻，博士
I'm impressed, doctor.
但是有惊无喜
But not the way you think.
后退，鲁格，不然我杀了他
Stand back, Ruk. I’ll kill him.
后退
Stay back.
鲁格
Ruk.
守卫
Protect.
罗杰！
Roger!
鲁格！不！
Ruk! No!
鲁格，停下， 科比博士说了你应该听我指挥
Ruk, stop. Dr. Korby said you are to obey me.
鲁格！
Ruk!
鲁格！我命令你不许伤害他
Ruk! I order you not to harm him.
寇克舰长
Captain Kirk.
你在哪儿？
Where are you?
寇克舰长，我能帮你
Captain Kirk. I can help you.
克莉丝汀，是你吗？
Christine, is that you?
舰长
Captain.
你比预计提前了
You finished ahead of schedule.
科比博士有很多货物要传送上舰
Dr. Korby has considerable cargo to beam aboard.
我得和他看一下我们的终点日程表
I'll have to go over our destination schedule with him.
你要和那个机器师傅一起回去？
You're going back down with the command packet?
别多管闲事了，史波克
Mind your own business, Mr. Spock.
你个杂种别来烦我了，听见没？
I'm sick of your half-breed interference. Do you hear?
- 听到了，舰长 - 你看起来有点郁闷，史波克
- Yes. Very well, captain. - You look upset, Mr. Spock.
- 没什么事吧？ - 没事，舰长
- Is everything all right up here? - No problems here, sir.
很好，我马上把科比博士一群人带上船
Good. I'll beam up shortly with Dr. Korby and party.
安全人员，我是史波克，外遣队准备如何？
Security, Spock here. Status of your landing party.
一切就绪，准备行动，长官
Ready and standing by, sir.
传送舰长下去后
Have them meet me in the transporter room
就让他们到传送室见我
after the captain has beamed down.
我看了一遍
I looked it over.
我想麦都思五行星是你绝佳的选择
I think you'll find planet Midos V an excellent choice.
一个小殖民地
A small colony,
有充足的原材料，你开了个好头，舰长
abundant raw materials. You've made a good beginning, captain.
谢谢，我在进取号上很自在
Thank you. I felt quite at home on the Enterprise.
安德烈娅…
Andrea...
吻我
...kiss me.
哦，不
Oh, no.
不
No.
不能听你摆布，没这条程序
Not programmed for you.
怎么了，安德烈娅？
What's the matter, Andrea?
困惑了？
Confused?
没有
No.
闹情绪了， 鲁格？
Emotion, Ruk?
你想杀我？敢违抗查佩尔小姐的命令？
You disapprove of Miss Chapel's orders to save my life?
让你活下去不合逻辑
To maintain your existence would be illogical.
为什么？
Why?
你的记忆库难道解不开这么一个简单的方程式？
Can't your memory banks solve a simple equation like that?
老一代人发生了什么，鲁格？
What happened to the Old Ones, Ruk?
太久之前的事了
So long ago.
他们会不会是把机器造得太好了？
Is it possible they built their machines too well?
让他们有了
Gave them pride
自尊和生存的欲望？
and a desire to survive?
机器人靠的是逻辑和秩序，却失望地发现
Machines that wanted logic and order and found that frustrated
他们的制造者是无逻辑又情绪化的生物
by the illogical, emotional creatures that built them?
是啊，那老一代人
Yes, the Old Ones.
我们的制造者
The ones who made us.
他们开始害怕我们
They grew fearful of us.
他们开始要关闭我们
They began to turn us off.
科比不就是在重蹈覆辙吗？
And isn't it Korby who's creating the same danger to you all over again?
与你们不同，人类感情充沛，行为不可预测
Unlike you, we humans are full of unpredictable emotions
无法用逻辑理解
that logic cannot solve.
对
Yes.
对，太过久远，我都忘了
Yes. It had been so long ago, I had forgotten.
老一代人在这里，我们的制造者，是啊
The Old Ones here, the ones who made us. Yes.
对，的确在我的记忆库里
Yes, it is still in my memory banks.
当时只有毁灭他们
It became necessary to destroy them.
你们行为变化莫测
You are inconsistent.
编程对你们无用
You cannot be programmed.
你们是劣等的
You are inferior.
- 科比呢？ - 你来自外部
- And Korby? - You came from the outside.
- 是你让这儿变得混乱无序 - 你的危险来自科比
- You bring disorder here. - The danger to you is Korby.
我是由科比编码的，我不能伤害他
I was programmed by Korby. I cannot harm him.
老一代人也对你编码了
The Old Ones programmed you too,
但也不是被你们毁灭了
but it became possible to destroy them.
这就是方程式
That was the equation.
生存！
Existence!
要存活就要消除编码
Survival must cancel out programming.
这就对了，鲁格，逻辑
That's it. Ruk, logic.
你不能保护想要摧毁你的人
You can't protect someone who's trying to destroy you.
鲁格，我想要…
Ruk, I would like--
你把他带到我们中间的
You brought him among us.
你带来了劣等种族
You brought the inferior ones.
我们清除了他们
We had cleansed ourselves of them.
你现在却带着讨厌的人回来了
And now you bring the evil back.
鲁格，停下
Ruk, stop.
你的程序
Your programming.
我别无选择
I had no choice.
你曾经尊重生命
You were a man with respect for all things alive.
我怎么解释你的变化？如果我告诉地球…
How can I explain the change in you? If I was to tell Earth
我是在你手里，告诉他们你变的…
that I was in your hands-- To tell them what has become--
我还是我，克莉丝汀
It's still me, Christine.
罗杰
Roger.
我在这儿
I'm in here.
你无法想象当时的情况
You can't imagine how it was.
我当时冷极了，快死了
I was frozen, dying.
我冻掉了双腿
My legs were gone.
我…只有我的大脑徘徊在生死之间
I was... I had only my brain between life and death.
这个可以修好
This can be repaired
比医治骨折的手指还要容易
easier than another man can set a broken finger.
我还是从前的我，克莉丝汀，也许更棒
I'm still the same as I was before, Christine. Perhaps even better.
是你吗，罗杰？
Are you, Roger?
- 安德烈娅 - 是，博士
- Andrea. - Yes, doctor.
有人在外交界处
There's someone in the outer junction.
史波克，他一定收到我的信息了
Spock. He must have got my message.
- 我去找鲁格 - 可他找不到我们，这简直就是迷宫
- I will find Ruk. - But he'll never find us in this maze.
鲁格被关闭了，找个武器自己应对
Ruk has been shut off. Get a weapon and deal with it.
守卫
Protect.
- 我想吻你 - 不
- I will kiss you. - No.
你…？
You...?
你不愿意？
You will not?
这不合逻辑
It is illogical.
我还是我，从里到外，每个部分
I'm the same. Direct transfer. All of me.
- 有人性，理智，却没有瑕疵 - 寇克逃出来了，我把他…
- Human, rational, but without a flaw. - Kirk freed himself, and I destroyed--
把他消灭了
Destroyed him.
我程序里没有报警系统
I am not programmed for alarms.
我听从并服从你的指挥
I listened to your instructions, obeyed them as stated.
她杀了那个机器人，科比，跟你杀鲁格一样
She killed the android, Korby, the same way you killed Ruk.
这就是你的完美世界吗？
Is this your perfect world?
你那些没有瑕疵的生物相互残杀？
Your flawless beings killing off one another?
这不就是你最厌恶的事吗？
Aren't you doing exactly what you hate most in humans,
像熄灭一盏灯一样肆无忌惮的杀戮？
killing with no more concern than when you turn off a light?
我不是机器
I am not a computer.
测试我吧
Test me.
让我来解决任何…
Ask me to solve any...
方程…
Equate.
发送信号啊
Transmit.
克莉丝汀，克莉丝汀，让我证明自己
Christine. Christine, let me prove myself.
这难道那么重要吗？
Does this make such a difference?
你不明白吗，罗杰？
Don't you see, Roger?
你做的每件事都表明这不是你
Everything you've done has proved it isn't you.
我就是罗杰·科比
I am Roger Korby!
那证明一下
Then prove it.
给我相位手枪
Give me that phaser gun.
如果你还有点人性，给我吧
If there's any human left in you, give it to me.
不
No.
你永远不会明白
You will never understand.
我制造了一个完美生物
I constructed a perfect being.
做过测试，做过证明
Tested it, proved it.
做过证明
Proved it.
安德烈娅，给我武器
Andrea, give me the weapon.
不，守卫
No. Protect.
守卫
Protect.
不
No.
去…去爱你
To-- To love you.
去…
To...
吻你
...kiss you.
不，你无法去爱
No, you cannot love.
你不是人类
You're not human.
爱你
Love you.
吻
Kiss.
寇克舰长
Captain Kirk.
在这里，史波克
In here, Spock.
舰长，你还好吧？
Captain, are you all right?
护士长？
Nurse?
科比博士在哪里？
Where's Dr. Korby?
科比博士…
Dr. Korby...
…从未出现
...was never here.
感谢你让我做决定，舰长
Thank you for letting me make the decision, captain.
我确定这是正确的选择
I'm quite certain I’m doing the right thing.
她留在船上
She's staying with the ship.
有烦心事，史波克先生？
Something bothering you, Mr. Spock?
坦白说，我听到你说“杂种”一词的时候
Frankly, I was rather dismayed
感到很沮丧，舰长
by your use of the term "half-breed," captain.
你可得知道，这种表达太不含蓄了 （史波克是瓦肯人和地球人的混血儿）
You must admit, it is an unsophisticated expression.
我会记住的，史波克先生…
I'll remember that, Mr. Spock...
…若下次还有类似情况
...the next time I find myself in a similar situation.
继续向前，舵手
Steady as we go, helm.
本集结束
-=The Last Fantasy=-
谢谢观赏